[Music]
so welcome to the fourth ruble wisdom
podcast this is going to be about the
intellectual dark web I'm kind of
assuming most of the people watching
this most of our audience will know what
the intellectual dialog is but I think
it's worth doing in a short introduction
it's sort of emerged from the sort of
network of thinkers you've got
unofficially in it you've got Eric
Weinstein Brett Weinstein Joe Rogan and
Dave Rubin Jordan Peterson sam Harris
Douglas Murray Majid Nawaz and a few
more names I mean there was there was a
few that were in the New York Times
article that kind of officially I guess
inaugurated as a concept I think we have
a slightly different take on what it is
and where it's going I think a lot of
people are looking at at the moment
through a sort of political lens and
it's a good first step because I think
what it does is these are all people
who've got a real kind of attachment to
free speech an attachment to having
difficult conversations about topics
that are increasingly difficult to have
in the mainstream media and what I think
it's done initially like the whole
phenomena of the intellectual Dartmouth
has showed up showing up how ideological
the media has become like some things
you can say some things you can't say
but I think there's a kind of mistake to
see it just through this political lens
which is I what I think a lot of the
people and descriptions of it have been
so far
yeah and it's ironic in a way because a
big one of the tenants of it is to move
beyond ideology and to be able to have
these discussions which are you know
free from that for me the really
interesting thing is what happens or
what's the direction we start moving in
when we begin to have these
conversations
beyond ideology this is where I think I
and we have a different understanding
about it because I see it potentially
moving towards a synthesis moving
towards a an intellectual synthesis and
someone like Jordan Peterson is a really
good starting point for this because he
already synthesizes so many different
ways of looking at the world
he integrates evolutionary biology
integrates psychology he integrates
mythology and religion and ends up in a
very similar place with all of them he
then kind of also brings in neuroscience
and says yeah well chaos and order even
the brain is divided between chaos and
order look at Ian McGilchrist it's work
the master in the emissary the left
brain the right brain there's there's a
there's a real integration happening
already with someone like Jordan
Pederson there was a really amazing
podcast with the day on the day Rubin
show with Ben Shapiro and Jordan
Peterson and then I've seen another
couple where Jordan Peterson was on Ben
Shapiro's podcast and what you see is
it's almost like Jordan Peterson kind of
absorbed than Shapiro in a way because
venture Piero's argument is sort of from
from revelation it's like okay we have
these moral truths that are kind of
given to us and Peterson was saying well
these moral truths also evolved but you
can look at kind of how morality evolves
but there is in some sense like a
revelation from above and a morality
that evolves and the two come together
and that there's some sort of sense of
like Peterson's conception of religion
and evolution and morality kind of
encompass been Shapiro's perspective and
he's able to say well yeah I'm not
saying you're wrong Ben but I also think
you can get there from many different
methods and that's all it was a really
like amazing thing to see like you could
just see the synthesis in action I mean
it's it's slightly kind of maybe unfair
to ben shapiro to say that Jordan Peters
absorbed it but Jordan Peterson had the
biggest frame and Ben Shapiro had a very
deep frame he's a very deep thinker but
his frame was then encompassed within
Jordan Peterson's and you could see the
the intellectual excitement of both of
them to have that conversation at then
Shapiro in particular the respect that
he had for Jordan Pederson and where he
was coming from
like really reframed and rather than
another level of depth potentially to
what what Ben Shapiro was already saying
and you do see a lot of the guys in the
intellectual dark web they have these
conversations and then when you watch
them on another podcast they're saying
something that sounds an awful lot like
someone they've heard before like so
people are sounding a lot more like
Jordan previous after we expect a lot of
time with it so there this is what I
feel the synthesis is is about but again
it can only happen if people are
prepared to to allow what is untrue to
burn off to do what Peterson says again
it's like are you willing to allow what
is false to burn off and to go through
the process of yeah of growth which is
always painful and I think there is a
shared understanding between all of the
or between lots of the members of the
intellectual dark web that there is
something called reality that we can
perceive that is independent of us as
perceivers which is you know that's that
for me has a lot of the energy and
excitement of it is moving away from
that postmodern mulch of radical radical
relativity and that is a key thing if
you want to burn away the Deadwood
because you have to that I mean inherent
in that is the idea that there is there
is something core beneath it and then
there is something that is true so again
it you know it is a reclaiming of truth
as well but I think a lot of them really
share otherwise why talk to get
somewhere you have to get towards
something that is independent of all of
us as perceivers and for me that's where
a lot of the power of it comes from and
what's fascinating is that you just get
a sense the people involved in this
conversation recognize something is
happening it's almost like a
conversation it's becoming self-aware
it's aware of itself and it's very
excited by Dave Reubens the classic
example is kind of like something's
going on the Internet's full of
foresters together and I don't believe
in kind of synchronicity but something's
happening and and I I think it's kind of
a Great Awakening you could you could
and I wonder whether you could almost
return it it's a great intellectual
awakening partly generated again it's
partly created by the internet ISM where
we now have the possibilities have three
our conversations we now have the
possibility to kind of follow the rabbit
hole as far down as it goes we have the
capability to now find it find ideas
outside the acceptable kind of surface
level mainstream of the mainstream media
and then go down these rabbit holes and
potentially be changed as a consequence
yeah I feel that energy with it when I
watch it and just you know engage with
it there is that sense of that kind of
electric sense of something happening
for me it's about the beginnings of
something happening it is something
happening but it's the beginnings of
something bigger and I think that's
where the excitement comes from like if
you look at a lot of the key players
they have had - they're talking about
their ideas in a very different way but
they've all had to embody their ideas to
some degree like Brett Weinstein had to
do something and stand up you know call
it Jordan Peterson of course actually do
a lot of things and it was under a lot
of pressure I think that's a really
interesting thing about it is that these
are people whose philosophy had to be
embodied in some way and I think that's
the direction we're moving in that's a
really good idea that's a really smart
way of looking at it because yeah it's
like these people have had to live out
their philosophies and Bret and Eric
Weinstein talked about it on the day
Reuben podcast which is an amazing
podcast watch it you haven't seen
already the what you've had is almost
this selection process for people who
are thinking outside the box because if
you if you insist that everyone uses a
certain set of pronouns I like the
Jordan Peter certainly you insist that
all white professors don't come into a
college on a certain day as they did
with Brett Weinstein what you'd find is
the people who are prepared to say no
are prepared to stand out against the
herd they are exactly the kind of people
who you need who are almost certain to
have created something extraordinary in
their work because they're they're
thinking differently and also I think
you also sort of touch on the idea that
this is the start of a conversation that
there is a deeper synthesis that
potentially there they're moving towards
so there's there's many levels to this
conversation and the intellectual dart
lab is sort of the it's almost like a
holding concept for the ongoing
conversation and it is a conversation
you've got throughout this this summer
and this year and ongoing you've got a
lot of these guys in conversation with
each other in very public venues and
effectively what what we're seeing is
kind of intellectual content becoming
like this happened a comedy in the 90
suddenly comedy came
the small clubs and was now kind of
selling out the o2 arena and Wembley and
all this sort of stuff and this is now
happening with intellectual content
which has to be a good thing but also so
there's there's the sense of okay this
conversation is happening but if this
conversation is not an open inquiry then
it's gonna fail I think and this is up
to everyone in the intellectual dark web
to make sure that this is the case it's
like so that what is the meta
conversation how do you have a meta
conversation that's genuinely generative
that's genuinely kind of potentially
finding a resolution and you have to be
the people involved like it takes a huge
amount of intellectual courage for
someone like sam harris to say you know
maybe I was a bit I was wrong about this
atheist thing he's made an entire career
and wrote several books about this so I
think at some point he's at least gonna
have to refrain kind of what he means
and accept that some kind of
metaphorical truth is also valuable as
well as scientific truth so this sense
of like open inquiry is is really
important it's like am i open to new
information or do I just keep trying to
kind of filter everything into what I
already think well you're not really an
intellectual unless you're willing to
release your previously held notions
when new information comes to light
that's what if that's what it really
should be I think and just just on the
on the rock stadium kind of feel of it
you know I was just thinking you know I
think it's interesting to look at the
energy that drives that many people to
want to go instead of seeing a concert
see an intellectual talk and what
strikes me about the whole thing and
about what they're doing on one level is
it's an inquiry into reality because
increasingly in a kind of post truth
world we don't have a sense of what
reality is you know practically
politically metaphysically and I think
there's a deep hunger for that and
that's again why that inquiry has to
remain open because reality is bigger
than the person perceiving it
contrary to the postmodern world view
which would say no it's it's all these
perceptions as the conversations
continue I hope
that what we will start to see is a real
is a growing synthesis between these
different perspectives and the
intellectual dark web and these are
really deep perspective this is why it's
another mistake to look at it through
the political lens is that these these
guys go right to the bedrock my Petersen
goes right to the bedrock Brett
Weinstein goes right to the bedrock in
terms of evolutionary biology
Eric Weinstein is a superstar
mathematician who I think probably has a
very different take on it because he's
seeing sort of he's seeing almost like
the source code and I think that's
probably why he originated that the
whole concept of the intellectual dart
web because he's seeing quite a long way
down the track but there's a few things
that then are holding up that synthesis
for example of jordan peterson and sam
harris there's a huge that that's a
really interesting conversation cuz cuz
if if they're both willing to do the
work and to give up like sam harris in a
very difficult position because i think
ultimately he is going to have to
concede that there are mythological
truths in religion as brett Weinstein
says they are mythologically true or
what'd he say
they're metaphorically true but literary
literally false sam house had been very
resistant to that perspective but i I
think going as this conversation
continues he's gonna find it
increasingly difficult to defend that
position so just a reverse back a bit to
what you're saying a second ago for me
one of the really interesting questions
is is it a synthesis like it is I think
a synthesis but also the way paradigm
shifts the way you know kuhn pointed out
paradigm shifts happen or when the
existing paradigm there's so much that
doesn't fit into it that the pressure
builds and eventually new one forms so
I'm just wondering where the you know
you just talked about Peterson and
Harris in a sense some worldview has to
give in in some way you know the
materialist paradigm potentially has to
give to something beyond that something
that integrates that but moves beyond it
and recognizes for example religion
and the transcendent so for me I think
that's where it could go is that the
synthesis also leads to something
shifting fundamentally in the way we
communicate and the way we you know an
ideas revolution as they talked about
you know for me that requires some
synthesis first but then some kind of
radical reevaluation as well how do we
how the hell do we find a way through
that chaos and how do we see reality
more clearly and I think that is an
overwhelming urge for millions of people
right now how do we see reality more
clearly and yeah to your point it has to
be done in a flexible open way because
reality is constantly shifting and I
think Peterson in particular understands
that but he talks about the humility of
understanding that you don't know enough
by definition that in a way God is fear
of God he talked about the interview
divided with him like what's what's the
real key to to true knowledge and I
suggested that kind of intellectual
courage was a big part of that and kind
of embodied knowledge as a big part of
that and he said that fear of God was
the beginning of wisdom and what he
meant by that was you always have to
remember as if your life depends on it
because it does that you don't know
enough and so there's it requires that
kind of level of humility so to
summarize we think that the intellectual
dark lever is a kind of placeholder for
an ongoing conversation that hopefully
will approach some kind of synthesis
like intellectual synthesis able to jump
between evolutionary biology and
psychology and all these different
things but ultimately saying well we're
looking at the same thing this is how
the world is but we can look at these
different ways mathematics and they're
ironing out at the moment hopefully that
ironing out all of this sort of
disagreements between them Sam Harris
you and Peterson all that sort of stuff
with the hope that they can reach this
kind of synthesis where does it go if
that's true what is what what comes next
I think ultimately the intellectual
synthesis is only one part and what
needs to happen is
kind of there's an embodied synthesis
that needs to come come in as well and
there's a there's a danger of it just
becoming an intellectual thing whereas
actually we know things are that core
like we don't know things from here we
know things in our gut we know things in
our emotions and there's an embodied
there's an embodied nature to true
knowing so I'm looking at people like
who are now not considered it part of
the intellectual diet web but I think a
holding really key parts of the puzzle
Richard Tarn as I mentioned before I
think kind of named it all really really
clearly back in the seventies I think
know a bit later if he was actually not
in the 90s you've got people like Stan
Grof who've been working with
psychedelic therapy and transformational
work since the since the 50s Jamie will
who we interviewed and we're about to
bring out another interview with soon he
he's a he works with flow states and he
works with transformational states that
I think is is is where we have to go
there are things we cannot understand
with just our minds and coming into the
body and also living and you know acting
out and putting these things into our
lives which you know Peterson talks
about a lot that is really for me the
next stage and philosophy used to be
like that before before Plato in
particular where it became about kind of
a discussion of ideas and they kind of
let's let's have a dialectic and let's
you know discuss these ideas which is
important but it's not enough it's not
enough they have to be lived as
something else happens when you do that
something very different happens and it
changes how we are in the world and it
also frees us from ideology and in a
very new way because ideology is a thing
of of the ego in the mind so if you stay
up there you can't undo ideology with
the mind really it comes from a much
deeper level and that's why it's
exciting to explore all these different
thinkers who are really at the cutting
edge of those practices and the cutting
edge of the science behind it as well
and also why we are increasingly doing
workshops yeah rebel wisdom has always
had the intellectual content and the
film's but also the work
shops and we're expanding that we've got
some amazing facilitators coming in
Louise Mazzanti from the glitch in the
matrix film and we've done a couple of
interesting interviews with her might be
solder raffia Turia we've got some
amazing people who have kind of going to
come and lead stuff for us so that's
really really exciting so we're
introducing a new section or stealing it
from Sam Harris
he calls it housekeeping which is kind
of like logistics and kind of what's
coming up and all the rest of it and
what's coming up is the first rebel
wisdom road trip in America we're flying
out to LA on Sunday the first and we're
out there for about two weeks so if
you're watching this new you're out
there la San Fran Bay Area or you can
suggest people that we should be
interviewing there we've already got
some amazing people lined up we're going
to see Jordan green haul a cure of the
Dom Richard Thomas Warren Farrell so
we've got a really amazing list of
interview interviewees already if you
can think of anyone that we should be
talking to then give us a shout or if
you are a rebel wisdom devotee let us
know we'll also have some merch with us
that we might be giving out t-shirts to
people so so yeah get in touch if you're
in the Bay Area or in on the west coast
you